[Music]
spearing is a microscopic blue green
algae whose carotenoid pigments are
responsible for the orange pink Hue of
flamingos at high enough doses it can
also turn us orange too like if we eat
too many carrots but it's considered
benign and goes away on its own when you
cut back the strangest color change I
ran across was this green br milk
following ingestion of blue green algae
whoa but thankfully that also disappears
after stopping spiran is said to have
various promising health effects at the
same time on the contrasting note there
are toxins that might contribute to
acute poisoning cancer liver damage and
gastrointestinal disturbances with
long-term consumption potentially
leading to Alzheimer's and Parkinson's
disease okay then and those purported
promised health effects like playing a
positive role in treating muscle cramps
are based on a study in which mice were
injected with faldy and
vinegar what can spirulina actually do
in people spirulina can improve
long-term blood sugar control in rats
but apparently not in humans also
disappointing when it comes to
anti-inflammatory or antioxidant effects
spirulina may help lower cholesterol
though perhaps due to reducing fat
absorption and lower blood pressures by
four or five points there was a recent
trial where mild to moderate Alzheimer's
patients were randomized to a gram
spirina or Placebo for 12 weeks and
appeared to end up slightly better off
cognitively than those in the control
group so those are some of the potential
upsides the concern is that although
algae supplements like blue green algae
chlorella and spirulina are all
advertised as being beneficial they
might be harmful because they may
contain algal toxin
though most toxins are found
contaminating the clth lake AFA Blu
green algae some toxins are found in
some spirin subs as well spirin samples
tested from markets around the world
have shown highly variable results
ranging from non- detection to alarming
levels of toxins the presence of toxin
producing algae contaminants is the most
likely explanation for the presence of
toxins in spirulina products because
producers cultivate spirulina in open in
outdoor ponds which are vulnerable to
contamination with toxin producing
species there have been calls for strict
quality control and monitoring but that
doesn't seem to have panned out this
study examined what was growing in five
commercial spirina products including
pills and Powers several potentially
pathogenic bacteria were detected in the
products and algae toxins were found in
all the products at levels that could
lead to Consumers exceeding the
recommended daily limits one study of
five protein powders with spiruline and
found that four of them even contain
bmaa which is a neurotoxin linked to
some Progressive neurod degenerative
diseases like ALS which I've talked
about
before yet spirina products continue to
be advertised as
detoxifiers though spirulina is commonly
contaminated the levels of toxins is
significantly lower than it's been found
in other Blu green algae supplements
nevertheless there's a concern that
long-term exposure to even very low
levels of these toxins may increase the
risk of liver cancer for example there
are also case reports of acute liver
damage tenderly tied to spirulina intake
as well as acute muscle damage and rare
autoimmune reactions to spirulina AFA
blue green algae or both including
blistering disorders too disturbing to
display
[Music]